A Guide to the Institutional review board oral history project collection, 2007-2008
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
Institutional review board oral history project collection
2007-2008
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
Schrag, Zachary M.
C0172
1 linear ft. (2 boxes)
Interviews conducted by Zachary Schrag for his book Ethical Imperialism: Institutional Review Boards and the Social Sciences, 1965 to the Present. Schrag interviewed key shapers of the institutional review board regime to raise important points about the effect of the IRB process on scholarship.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Zachary Schrag in 2009.
Historical Information
University researchers in the United States seeking to observe, survey, or interview people are required first to complete ethical training courses and submit their proposals to an institutional review board (IRB). Under current rules, IRBs have the power to demand modifications under the threat of the denial of funding, degrees, or promotion if their recommended modifications to scholars' proposals are not followed.
Scope and Content
Interviews conducted by Zachary Schrag for his book Ethical Imperialism: Institutional Review Boards and the Social Sciences, 1965 to the Present. Schrag interviewed key shapers of the institutional review board regime to raise important points about the effect of the IRB process on scholarship.
Arrangement
Organized into two series.
Series 1: Interview Transcripts, 2007-2008
Series 2: Audiovisual, 2007-2008
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives holds an extensive oral history collection, some of which documents university policy in the United States.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Institutional review boards (Medicine).; Social sciences--Research--Moral and ethical aspects--United States.
Document Types:
Sound recordings.
Contents List
- Series 1: Interview Transcripts, 2007-2008
  This series contains the hard copy transcripts of the interviews.
  - Tom L. Beauchamp Interview Transcript, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Transcript of IRB interview between Zachary Schrag and Tom L. Beauchamp, a consultant for the National Commission for the Protection of Human Subjects of Biomedical and Behavioral Research, 1974-1978.
  - Bradford Gray Interview Transcript, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Transcript of IRB interview between Zachary Schrag and Bradford Gray, the Staff Sociologist for the National Commission for the Protection of Human Subjects of Biomedical and Behavioral Research, 1974-1978.
  - Albert Jonsen Interview Transcript, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Transcript of IRB interview between Zachary Schrag and Albert Jonsen, the Commissioner of the National Commission for the Protection of Human Subjects of Biomedical and Behavioral Research, 1974-1978.
  - Barbara Mishkin Interview Transcript, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Transcript of IRB interview between Zachary Schrag and Barbara Mishkin, Assistant Staff Director for the National Commission for the Protection of Human Subjects of Biomedical and Behavioral Research, 1974-1978.
  - Gary B. Ellis Interview Transcript, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Transcript of IRB interview between Zachary Schrag and Gary B. Ellis, the director of the Office for Protection from Research Risks from 1993 to 2000.
  - Cornelius E. Gallagher Interview Transcript, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Transcript of IRB interview between Zachary Schrag and Congressman Cornelius E. Gallagher. Gallagher was the representative for New Jersey's 13th congressional district from 1959 to 1973.
  - John M. Kennedy Interview Transcript, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Transcript of IRB interview between Zachary Schrag and John M. Kennedy, chairman of the Committee on Professional Ethics at the American Sociological Association in the 1990s.
  - Jonathan Knight Interview Transcript, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Transcript of IRB interview between Zachary Schrag and Jonathan Knight, staff member of the American Association of University Professors from 1977 to 2008.
  - Herbert Phillips Interview Transcript, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Transcript of IRB interview between Zachary Schrag and Herbert Phillips, IRB chairman from the University of California, Berkeley in the early 1970s.
  - Joan P. Porter Interview Transcript, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Transcript of IRB interview between Zachary Schrag and Joan P. Porter, the executive coordinator for interagency affairs in the Office for Protection from Research Risks in the 1980s and 1990s.
- Series 2: Audiovisual, 2007-2008
  This series contains the audio recordings of interviews and text files of the transcripts.
  - Audio recordings and text files of IRB interviews, 2007-2008 (Box 1)
    Three DVDs. Two contain the audio recordings of the IRB interviews, the third contains text files of the transcripts of those interviews.